A Guide to the Papers of Olivia Davis, 1955-1980
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Olivia Davis 1955-1980
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
13389
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was received as a gift to the Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections at the University of Virginia Library from Miranda Wiebusch, Stafford, Va. on August 14, 2005.
Biographical/Historical Information
Olivia Davis, daughter of the portrait painter Henry Carr, was born in England and lived there until World War II when she met and married an American lawyer. She wrote, The Last of the Greeks, Steps to the Sun, and had short stories published in books and leading literary journals. She and her family lived in Springfield, Virginia.
Scope and Content
The collection, 1.5 linear feet, 3 Hollinger boxes and ca. 107 items, includes 33 short stories and two unfinished manuscripts, Long After Bedtime and Unequal Voices written by Olivia Davis. Some of the short stories contain rejection notices from various publishers.
One of the manuscripts, Unequal Voices, has many versions and several titles such as, Unequal Voices, Secret Societies, and Renata. It tells the story of a family living in England at the outbreak of World War II amidst air raids and bombings. In the beginning the parents are in love with each other and their children have dreams of success and romance but as time passes and the war is upon them, they experience disappointments.
After the war, they struggle with the acceptance of their relationships as a collection of familiar patterns and mutual understandings or yielding to an excitement and passion that surrounds romantic love. Some of the characters are unhappily married, divorced, unmarried, happily married, homosexual or in love with other spouses.
There are miscellaneous news clippings and a license agreement between Marcia Lerner and Olivia Davis for the sale of the publication of The Other Child for production by Marcia Lerner.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by title of each manuscript. License agreements and news clippings are also filed alphabetically with the manuscripts.
Contents List
- All the Fun in the World, 1976 July 6, 2 drafts 18 pp. (9 pp. each). (Box-folder 1:1)
- Another Part of the Garden, 1978 April, Several drafts 20 pp. (Box-folder 1:2)
- Breathing Space (other names: Free Verse, Poetic License, Roots, Death of an Artist,) 1976 March, 1 item 17 pp. (Box-folder 1:3)
- Breathing Space, 1978 April 14, 1 item 6 pp. (Box-folder 1:4)
- Breathing Space with notes and rejection notice, n. d., 3 drafts. 20 pp., 21 pp., 14 pp., 35 pp. (Box-folder 1:5)
- The Cup-Bearers, 1976 July 3, 3 drafts. 39 total pp. (Box-folder 1:6)
- Do Not Block Jackson Street, n. d., 1 item. 3 pp. (Box-folder 1:7)
- Double Vision, 1975 August, 1 item. 26 pp. (Box-folder 1:8)
- The Edge of the Cliff, n. d., 1 item. 5 pp. (Box-folder 1:9)
- Flowers in Late Summer (Clones or Babies), 1978 May; n. d., 2 drafts. 29 total pp. (Box-folder 1:10)
- The Fortunate Ones, n. d., 1 item. 12 pp. (Box-folder 1:11)
- The French Town Car, n. d., 1 item. 12 pp. (Box-folder 1:12)
- Goat's Walk, n. d., 1 item. 7 pp. (Box-folder 1:13)
- Growing Up Happy, Way Down There, 1979 May 9, n. d., 3 drafts 49 total pp. (Box-folder 1:14)
- I Met a Magician, n. d. [pre-war], 2 drafts. 17 total pp. (Box-folder 1:15)
- Illusions or the Good Cheap Life with rejection notice, 1979 February; [1980], 2 drafts. 54 total pp. (Box-folder 1:12)
- The Ingrate, n. d., 1 item. 25 pp. (Box-folder 1:13)
- Jealousies, n. d., 1 item. 12 pp. (Box-folder 1:14)
- Kitty's Things, 1975 November 8; 1980 September, n. d., 6 drafts, 82 total pp. (Box-folder 1:15)
- License Agreement for the sale of The Other Child from Olivia Davis to Marcia Lerner for production, 1980 September 29, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:16)
- The Local Boys, 1977 March 11, March 18; 1979 February 17; n. d., 5 drafts. 109 total pp. (Box-folder 1:17)
- Long After Bedtime, Texas novel (miscellaneous parts), n. d., 1 item. 100 pp. (Box-folder 1:18)
- Long After Bedtime, Texas novel (miscellaneous parts), n. d., 1 item. 70 pp. (Box-folder 2:1)
- Luke and Jane, n. d., 1 item. 5pp. (Box-folder 2:2)
- Miscellaneous typed pages, n. d., 1 item. 5 pp. (Box-folder 2:3)
- News clippings and notes, n. d., 7 articles and notes. 30 pp. (Box-folder 2:4)
- News Release of the Mattachine Society of Washington, 1962 August 28, 1 item. 2 pp. (Box-folder 2:5)
- Oft-Bitten, n. d., 1 item. 21 pp. (Box-folder 2:6)
- Only in the Annex, n. d., 1 item. 14 pp. (Box-folder 2:7)
- An Ordinary Friendship, n. d., 1 item. 15 pp. (Box-folder 2:8)
- Peter's Visit Home, n. d., 1 item. 8 pp. (Box-folder 2:9)
- The Playmate, n. d., Miscellaneous parts. 17 pp. (Box-folder 2:10)
- Poems, n. d., 7 poems and notes. 8pp. (Box-folder 2:11)
- Running Away to Warsaw, 1979 April 6, 1 item. 13 pp. (Box-folder 2:12)
- The Science Fair-and Unfair, n. d., 1 item. 16 pp. (Box-folder 2:13)
- Short Story Fragments, n. d., Miscellaneous parts of various stories; 50 pp. (Box-folder 2:14)
- A Stranger in the Street, n. d., 1 item. 13 pp. (Box-folder 2:15)
- That's My Paper Bag! 1965 February; n. d., 2 drafts. 13 total pp. (Box-folder 2:16)
- The Tour, n. d., 3 drafts. 30 pp. (Box-folder 2:17)
- Trouble at the Montagues, n. d., 1 draft. 6 pp. (Box-folder 2:18)
- Tuppeny Fare and the Nurse's Tale, [pre WWI], 1 draft. 12 pp. (Box-folder 2:19)
- Unequal Voices, n. d., 2 drafts. 110 total pp. (Box-folder 2:20)
  Renata's childhood.
- Unequal Voices The Office, n. d., 1 item. 43 pp. (Box-folder 2:21)
- Unequal Voices. The Office, n. d., 1 item. 103 pp. (Box-folder 2:22)
- Unequal Voices. The Office, n. d., 1 item. 58 pp. (Box-folder 2:23)
- Unequal Voices. The Office, n. d., 1 item. 98 pp. (Box-folder 2:24)
- Unequal Voices, n. d., 1 item. 65 pp. (Box-folder 2:25)
  Rachel/Julia/Elizabeth meet Philip; Philip's marriages.
- Unequal Voices, n. d., Weekend with Philip. (Box-folder 2 drafts. 85 pp.)
- Unequal Voices (Stained Glass), n. d., 2 drafts. 16 total pp. (Box-folder 3:1)
  Philip and his son.
- Unequal Voices. Renata's funeral, n. d., 2 drafts. 104 total pp. (Box-folder 3:2)
  (Visit with Philip).
- Unequal Voices. Renata's funeral, n. d., 3 drafts. 152 total pp. (Box-folder 3:3)
  (Visit with Kathleen, meeting of Philip's son, visit with Andrew, reflection of Ralph and Freer and return home.)
- Unequal Voices, n. d., 1 item. 55 pp. (Box-folder 3:4)
  Julia goes abroad to take care of her mother, Edith when she has a stroke.
- Unequal Voices, n. d., 1 item. 100 pp. (Box-folder 3:5)
  Edith first meets Quentin and memories of World War I.
- Unequal Voices, n. d., 1 item. 102 pp. (Box-folder 3:6)
  Valentina and Mexico. Rachel's husband Murray is shot.
- Unequal Voices, n. d., Miscellaneous pages. 100 pp. (Box-folder 3:7)
- Viva Orozco. A Lady of Sad Countenance, n. d., 5 drafts. 100 total pp. (Box-folder 3:8)
- What I Did on My Summer Vacation and rejection notice, [1969], 1 item. 15 pp. (Box-folder 3:9)
- Women's Page, n. d., 2 drafts. 34 total pp. (Box-folder 3:10)